<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The unlawfulness of stretching forth the hand to resist or murder princes with the principal cases about resistance, considered, in two sermons : the first preacht upon the last thirtieth of January, the other, upon the day of thanksgiving, for the deliverance of the King and kingdom from the late treasonable conspiracy / by William Payne ...</title>
            <author>Payne, William, 1650-1696.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56751</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P912</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22908</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12745141</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12745141</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93236</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56751)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93236)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 727:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The unlawfulness of stretching forth the hand to resist or murder princes with the principal cases about resistance, considered, in two sermons : the first preacht upon the last thirtieth of January, the other, upon the day of thanksgiving, for the deliverance of the King and kingdom from the late treasonable conspiracy / by William Payne ...</title>
                  <author>Payne, William, 1650-1696.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A. Grover for Walter Kittilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>A sermon upon the thirtieth of January, 1683 : being the day of the martyrdom of King Charles I -- A sermon upon the thanksgiving for the deliverance of the King and kingdom from the late treasonable conspiracy.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Government, Resistance to --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Kings and rulers --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93236:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93236:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE UNLAWFULNESS OF Stretching forth the Hand TO <hi>Reſiſt or Murder</hi> PRINCES, WITH THE Principal Caſes about <hi>RESISTANCE,</hi> CONSIDERED, In Two SERMONS.</p>
            <p>The Firſt Preacht upon the Laſt Thirtieth of <hi>January.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other, upon the Day of <hi>Thanksgiving,</hi> for the Deliverance of the King and Kingdom from the Late <hi>Treaſonable Conſpiracy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>WILLIAM PAYNE</hi> Rector of St. <hi>Mary White-Chappel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>A. Grover,</hi> for <hi>Walter Kittilby</hi> at the
<hi>Biſhop</hi>'s-<hi>Head</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church-yard.</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:93236:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93236:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE HONOURABLE Sir <hi>WILLIAM SCROGGS</hi> Late Lord Chief Juſtice of ENGLAND.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Could be very <hi>glad</hi> that I had leſs <hi>Reaſon</hi> to juſtifie the publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of theſe <hi>Sermons,</hi> and that they were altogether as
<hi>unſeaſonable,</hi> as the putting out of Bills to Cure the <hi>Plague,</hi> when no Body is
<hi>Sick</hi> or <hi>Dies</hi> of it, but <hi>Treaſon</hi> is a Diſeaſe that
<pb facs="tcp:93236:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Rages</hi> amongſt us, and though it be not like the
<hi>Sweating-Sickneſs</hi> of old, a Malady <hi>peculiar</hi> to <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men, yet the
<hi>plenty</hi> and <hi>Luxury</hi> of our Country may perhaps make us more <hi>Subject</hi> to it then others: Were I able to preſcribe any thing, however ordinary, that was likely to be either a
<hi>Remedy</hi> or an <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidote</hi> againſt it, I ſhould think it my Duty as a Lover of the <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> of Mankind, as a Lover of my <hi>King</hi> and
<hi>Country,</hi> and as a Miniſter of that <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> which has been often the <hi>Mark,</hi> but never the <hi>Author</hi> of any Treaſon; and I hope the <hi>good meaning</hi> of this Endeavour will compound for the <hi>weakneſs</hi> of it, and its
<hi>Honeſty</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> cover the Multitude of its <hi>Faults</hi> and
<hi>Imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi> I thought my ſelf more then ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily concerned to do this when the
<hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:93236:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>had ſo largely ſpread at our end of the <hi>Town</hi> and in my own
<hi>Pariſh,</hi> where two of the Conſpirators that are Executed, and two others that are in the <hi>Proclamation</hi> had their laſt Abodes; for though this, does not like other
<hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagions,</hi> begin in <hi>Alleys</hi> and the <hi>Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parts,</hi> among the <hi>Poor</hi> and Ordinary Perſons, yet the <hi>Great</hi> ones make it their Buſineſs to <hi>ſpread</hi> it among thoſe, and there it <hi>ſettles,</hi> and there it generally <hi>breaks out.</hi> Had
<hi>theſe</hi> Men come to our <hi>Churches</hi> they had learnt other Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, then what I am afraid, they have done elſewhere; and that none may be ſo <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litious</hi> as to think we calculate our <hi>Sermons</hi> merely for the preſent <hi>Circumſtances,</hi> as if the
<hi>Pulpit</hi> were but a kind of <hi>wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-glaſs,</hi> wherein the Doctrine of
<hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience</hi> to Governours is higher or lower according to the <hi>temperature</hi> or
<hi>Varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:93236:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>of outward Affairs, I have put out a plain <hi>Sermon</hi> without any addition or alteration, that was Preacht long before the <hi>Plot,</hi> when I little thought of having any ſuch occaſion to make it <hi>publick;</hi> I thought then, and do ſo now, that thoſe Obvious and Familiar things, which every one muſt uſe on that <hi>Subject,</hi> would do good; but there remained a harder part, which was to <hi>keep</hi> the good <hi>Seed</hi> I had ſowed clear from the Weeds that are apt to grow up and <hi>choke</hi> it, for <hi>Treaſon</hi> has
<hi>ſtood</hi> ſo long, without being cut down, eſpecially in the late Times that it has
<hi>run</hi> to <hi>ſeed,</hi> and <hi>ſcattered</hi> its Principles that will not fail to
<hi>nouriſh</hi> and <hi>make</hi> it <hi>grow</hi> again, and I thought the only way to
<hi>deſtroy</hi> it, was to <hi>pluck</hi> up thoſe by the <hi>Rootes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:93236:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>I know,</hi> My Lord, the <hi>Subject</hi> will commend it ſelf to your
<hi>Patronage,</hi> whoſe Loyalty to your Prince is ſo well <hi>known</hi> to all, that as it was always your <hi>vertue,</hi> ſo it has been ſometimes your Crime; and who have ſo well ſhown your Zeal and Abhorrence of all Plots and Treaſons in the late <hi>Popiſh</hi> one, where your <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Eloquence</hi> were too hard for the cunningeſt of
<hi>Traitors,</hi> and the <hi>Prieſts</hi> found your <hi>Reaſon</hi> out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doe their
<hi>Infallibility;</hi> yet I ſhould not have preſumed to offer theſe Diſcourſes unto your Lordſhips hands, who is not only ſo great a <hi>Judge</hi> but ſo great a
<hi>Maſter</hi> of <hi>ſence</hi> and of <hi>ſpeaking,</hi> but that I <hi>know</hi> your
<hi>Candour</hi> and <hi>Mercy</hi> is equal to your <hi>Judgment,</hi> ſo that what has inclined you to <hi>approve</hi> and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage me in ſome other things of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb facs="tcp:93236:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>will I queſtion not, prompt you, at leaſt to <hi>excuſe</hi> me in this.</p>
            <p>The Extraordinary <hi>kindneſs</hi> and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility you have been pleaſed to ſhow me, would require a much better Teſtimony of my <hi>Obſervance</hi> and <hi>Gratitude,</hi> then this, which is the only one I can pay at preſent, and therefore muſt beg you to <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept</hi> it from, <hi>My Lord,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt Obedient, and moſt Obliged Servant</hi> William Payne.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93236:5"/>
            <head>A SERMON UPON THE Thirtieth of <hi>JAN<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ARY,</hi> 1683. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Day of the
<hi>Martyrdom</hi> OF King Charles I.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 SAM. 26.9.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For who can ſtretch forth his Hand againſt the Lord's anointed, and be guiltleſs?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>RELIGION, as it makes Proviſion for us in another World; and is the only Means to ſecure us a good State after this Life; a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and eternal Happineſs for our Souls; ſo 'tis that alſo upon which the preſent Welfare, the Comfort and Felicity of this Life does chiefly depend;
'tis that which ſupports the World, and preſerves the Peace and Order, the Quiet, and good Settlement of it; 'tis that which ſets a Guard about our Lives, and all our Enjoyments, and reſtrains Mankind from
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:93236:6"/>ravening and devouring one another: 'Tis that which is the main Strength, the true Foundation of <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> which ſupports the Princes <hi>Throne,</hi> and Guards it like an Angel from the Sons of Violence; and as it obliges us to all thoſe Duties of Right and Juſtice, that are neceſſary for the Good and Welfare of all Mankind; ſo it eſpecially ſecures and maintains the <hi>Rights of Princes</hi> and Governours; which cannot be violated without the greateſt Miſchief, and the moſt pernicious Conſequences to the World.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>David,</hi> who was the moſt ſingular Example of all Religion and Piety to God; who was the great Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample and Teacher of it to the <hi>Jewiſh Church;</hi> and who has left ſuch Memorials and Monuments of it, as make up a great part of the Devotion and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of all Chriſtians: Him was God pleaſed to make as great an Example of Loyalty to his <hi>Prince,</hi> and of Duty and Obedience to his <hi>Sovereign;</hi> and that pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the ſame Principles of
<hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Conſcience</hi> that made him ſo to God. He had the leaſt Reaſon otherwiſe to be ſo to his <hi>Prince</hi> that could be well i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magined: Who ſought to take away his Life unjuſtly; he hunted him as a Partridge upon the Mountains, and intended to make him a Prey to his unreaſonable Fury and Diſpleaſure. Who would have taken away that Right which God had expreſly given him; and deprived him of the <hi>Succeſſion to the Crown,</hi> which Heaven had entituled him to. Who deſtroyed all his Friends he could light of, and <hi>murdered fourſcore and five of the Prieſts of the Lord in one day</hi> upon his account. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi>
22.18. <hi>Who put a whole City to the ſword, Man, Woman and Child,</hi> v. 19. and exerciſed all the Acts of Cruelty and Injuſtice to him, and all thoſe that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:93236:6"/> How much leſs than all this would have ſerved ſome Men to fly out into open <hi>Reſiſtance</hi> and <hi>Rebellion</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Governours? Yet he that was appointed by God's immediate Command, to be the next Heir of the Kingdom, and was anointed by
<hi>Samuel</hi> to that purpoſe, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.12. So that in his Life and Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the common Welfare and Intereſt, the Safety of the whole Kingdom of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was concerned: Nay, he that was the <hi>General of Iſrael,</hi> and a great Officer under <hi>Saul;</hi> and to ſuch Magiſtrates more inferiour than <hi>David</hi> was in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſome People are for giving a Power to <hi>reſtrain</hi> and <hi>reſiſt</hi> the Superiour Magiſtrate; yet he under theſe Circumſtances, which if any, would make it lawful and juſtifiable to have done otherwiſe, he then only <hi>fled away,</hi> and made no manner of <hi>Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> to
<hi>Saul,</hi> who was his <hi>Prince,</hi> tho' he was like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe his <hi>unjuſt Perſecutor:</hi> And to ſhew that he did this out of <hi>Conſcience</hi> and
<hi>Religion,</hi> and not for <hi>want of Power,</hi> or Ability to do otherwiſe (which is the only Reaſon that ſome men have againſt <hi>reſiſting</hi>) God was pleaſed to put
<hi>Saul</hi> into his Hands at the Cave in <hi>Engedi;</hi> and to give him an Opportunity to have done what he would with him; and the men that were then with him, would have perſuaded him, That this was a Providence of God that ſhewed he would have the thing done, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.4.
<hi>And the men of</hi> David <hi>ſaid unto him, behold the day of which the Lord ſaid unto thee, Behold I will deliver thine Enemy into thine Hand, that thou mayeſt do to him as it ſhall ſeem good to thee.</hi> How would a much leſs <hi>Providence</hi> have been thought enough to make this lawful, and a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Indication of the Will of God to ſome men who had no ſuch
<hi>promiſe</hi> at all as that was? but <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> was a better Interpreter, both of God's
<hi>promiſe,</hi> and of his <hi>providence</hi> too; and he dared not touch the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93236:7"/>perſon, or the Life of his <hi>Sovereign;</hi> but only cut off the Hem of his Garment; and for that <hi>his Heart ſmote him</hi> afterwards at the 5th. <hi>verſe.</hi> It were well if ſome Mens Hearts would ſmite them, who have cut off not <hi>the Hem of their Sovereign's Garment,</hi> but <hi>his Royal Head from his Body;</hi> and yet their Hearts are ſo harden'd, that they have ſhown, moſt of them, but little Repentance for it.</p>
            <p>But this was not enough; <hi>David</hi> might have loſt this Opportunity perhaps out of Unadviſedneſs, or Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudence, and have been ſorry for it afterwards; or it might not have been ſo fit to have diſpatch'd ſo great a Work at that time; or he had not time to delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and conſider well what was to be done with ſo lucky an Advantage. Behold, God tries him ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time at <hi>Hachilah,</hi> where <hi>Saul</hi> had pitched his Tents in purſuit of
<hi>David,</hi> who was in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs hard by: There <hi>David</hi> in the Night comes with
<hi>Abiſhai</hi> into the Camp of <hi>Saul,</hi> and finds the Souldiers ſo careleſs and ſleeping, that he got into the very Trench where <hi>Saul lay ſleeping, with his ſpear by him, ſtuck at his Bolſter in the ground, and</hi> Abner, <hi>and his other Captains and Guards aſleep by him.</hi> Here <hi>Abiſhai</hi> indeed was in the mind of other men, not to ſpare their <hi>Sovereign</hi> when they have got him into their power. Then ſaid <hi>Abiſhai</hi> unto <hi>David, God hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered thine enemy into thine hand this day; now there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let me ſmite him, I pray thee, with the ſpear, even to the earth at once, and I will not ſmite him the ſecond time:</hi> But <hi>David,</hi> from the ſame Principles of <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> that had reſtrained him before, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids any ſuch thing, as containing the moſt horrid Sin and Guilt in it; and this alſo from a Reaſon that holds good as to all
<hi>Sovereign Princes</hi> and Governours whatever: And <hi>David ſaid to</hi> Abiſhai,
<hi>Deſtroy him
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:93236:7"/>not; for who can ſtretch forth his hand againſt the Lords anointed and be guiltleſs?</hi> This Example of <hi>David</hi> is very full, and comes up to the greateſt Caſes, and allows of no Exceptions that can well be thought of to this his general
<hi>Principle;</hi> and from that I ſhall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to you theſe two things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The great Unlawfulneſs of reſiſting, or draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Sword againſt the Sovereign Prince.</item>
               <item>2. The horrid Guilt of murdering him, and taking away his Life.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Stretching out the Hand</hi> is a Phraſe may fairly be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of <hi>both</hi> thoſe; tho' I confeſs it is here prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally meant of the later; but 'tis the Firſt is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally the Cauſe of the other, and the Principle that leads to it; He that ſtretches forth his Hand ſo far as to <hi>reſiſt</hi> his Prince, will ſtretch it a little farther to
<hi>murder</hi> him too, if it be in his Power, and he finds it neceſſary for his Deſigns. I ſhall therefore firſt ſhew the unlawfulneſs of <hi>reſiſting</hi> the Prince, or drawing the Sword againſt him; and if we once make that good, we ſecure him from all
<hi>Attempts and Outrages upon his Life:</hi> And this upon ſeveral Accounts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. From the Practice and Example of the <hi>wiſeſt and beſt</hi> Men, who under the
<hi>moſt hard and unjuſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſages,</hi> the <hi>moſt cruel Sufferings</hi> from their Governors; and in the worſt Caſes that can well be put, yet always ſubmitted patiently, and never made uſe of any <hi>Force,</hi> or <hi>violent Reſiſtance</hi> againſt them. I have prevented my ſelf in the Inſtance of <hi>David,</hi> which is ſo conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable as may ſerve for a full Example of this under the <hi>Old Teſtament;</hi> tho' I might here mention the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour of the <hi>Jews,</hi> under the <hi>Bondage and Cruelty of Pharaoh,</hi> who when he oppreſt them unmercifully, and murdered their Children as ſoon as born; and gave them the greateſt Provocations to have freed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93236:8"/>themſelves, yet they never made any Attempts that way; tho' by
<hi>Pharoah</hi>'s own Confeſſion, they were more and mightier than the <hi>Egyptians</hi> themſelves, <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.9. But I chooſe rather to offer you what more concerns us Chriſtians; tho' it would be a great Shame if we ſhould come ſhort in this of the murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and ſtiff necked, and <hi>Rebellious Jews;</hi> and that is the <hi>Example of Chriſt and his Apoſtles,</hi> and the <hi>Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chriſtians;</hi> which as they are Patterns to us of all thoſe Vertues that they taught and commanded; ſo eſpecially of <hi>Loyalty, Obedience,</hi> and <hi>patient Submiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> to the Governours which God had ſet over them; and this is more remarkable in them, becauſe they hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to live under ſuch Governours as were the moſt notorious for all manner of <hi>Wickedneſs,</hi> and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially for <hi>Cruelty and Injuſtice;</hi> and that moſt <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly to them,</hi> as well as others; and yet even un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Tiberius,</hi> whom <hi>Suetonius</hi> relates, as a Man infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, not only for Cruelty to his neareſt Relations, but even for ſuch Luſts and Debaucheries as were not fit to be related; our Bleſſed Saviour ſhew'd himſelf a <hi>quiet and obedient Subject,</hi> and paid Tribute at the Expence even of a Miracle, <hi>Matth.</hi> 17.27. And under the Emperor's Preſident, which was <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> he patiently ſuffered a moſt cruel and ſhameful Death, that he was no ways worthy of; and which he could have reſcued himſelf from by a <hi>Legion of Angels,</hi> had he pleaſed; but he neither thought fit to make uſe of them, or his Diſciples, to deliver him from the Hands of Violence and Injuſtice; but had occaſion to ſhew his Diſlike of all ſuch Deſigns, and of all manner of <hi>reſiſting,</hi> or making uſe of the Sword againſt the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of our Governours, in that famous Caſe of St.
<hi>Peter, Matt.</hi> 26.51, 52. who, when in Defence of his <hi>Maſter,</hi> againſt thoſe who came to apprehend
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93236:8"/>him, he drew his Sword, and ſmote a Servant of the High Prieſt, and cut off his Ear. <hi>Jeſus</hi> made Amends for it by a Miracle, and commanded him <hi>to put up his ſword into its place;</hi> and that with a Declaration that does for ever condemn the making uſe of the Sword againſt the Authority of the Magiſtrate, tho' it be to defend an innocent perſon from the greateſt Injury: <hi>For all they that take the ſword, ſhall periſh by the ſword,</hi> that is, who take it againſt their <hi>Rulers,</hi> or <hi>thoſe whom they appoint</hi> or commiſſion: For this was not againſt the High Prieſt himſelf, but his Servant; and neither was he the Supreme Governour at that time.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Apoſtles</hi> of our Saviour followed this excellent Example of their Bleſſed Maſter, when all of them, except one, ſuffered Martyrdom, under that Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that they ſo quietly ſubmitted to; and ſo far was St. <hi>Paul</hi> from <hi>reſiſting,</hi> that he repented of an ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty and inconſiderate Word, that he ſpake againſt the High Prieſt,
<hi>who was judging him againſt the Law,</hi> Acts 23.5. And never did St. <hi>Peter</hi> pretend any ſuch power, by Vertue of his <hi>Supremacy,</hi> as ſome that call themſelves <hi>his Succeſſors</hi> have done ſince; nor in any of the firſt and beſt Ages of Chriſtianity were there any <hi>Tumults,</hi> or <hi>Seditions,</hi> or <hi>Factions</hi> made againſt the Government, tho' they were vaſtly numerous, and had fill'd, as <hi>Tertullian</hi> tells the Heathens themſelves, all their Cities, and Caſtles, and all the places and parts of the Empire; yet <hi>Nunquam Albiniani, vel Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiam, vel Caſſiani inveniri potuerunt Chriſtiani,</hi> No Chriſtians were ever of the Number of any of the Movers of <hi>Treaſon</hi> or
<hi>Sedition,</hi> of <hi>what Party ſoever:</hi> They endured unheard of <hi>Cruelties</hi> from their Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours; the greateſt <hi>Tortures</hi> that the Wit and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of their Enemies could invent; and this often, as they complained in their <hi>Apologies, againſt Law too,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:93236:9"/>ſuch as would have ſtirr'd up thoſe who had <hi>power to defend themſelves,</hi> had they not learn'd ſuch <hi>Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> from their Religion as forbad it; and theſe were then ſo powerful upon their Minds, being no doubt often inculcated by their Teachers, as made <hi>ſeven thouſand Souldiers,</hi> who were Chriſtians in
<hi>Maximia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> his Army, to ſuffer themſelves to be all <hi>ſlain and murdered</hi> for the ſake of their Religion, when they were all <hi>armed,</hi> and in a poſture to have
<hi>reſiſted by force,</hi> and defended themſelves. More famous and greet Examples I might give of this; but in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond place.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This was a Chriſtian Principle, and a <hi>Command of the Goſpel,</hi> upon which they grounded their Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and Submiſſion to their Governours; elſe their Example would not be ſo conſiderable; but might ſeem to have proceeded from <hi>Weakneſs and Inability,</hi> from Timorouſneſs and Caution, or the like; but no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is a plainer, or more peremptory Command in the whole Goſpel, than to be obedient to our Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and not to reſiſt them. I need name but that very well known place, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 1 <hi>Let every ſoul be ſubject to the higher powers;</hi> and at the Second, <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever reſiſteth the Power, reſiſteth the Ordinance of God, and they that reſiſt, ſhall receive to themſelves Damnation; and that this</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is not only a temporal, but a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and Eternal Judgment, is plain from the fifth Verſe, <hi>Wherefore ye muſt neeeds be ſubject, not only for Wrath, but even for Conſcience ſake:</hi> Not only for Fear of that preſent Danger you may otherwiſe incur; but alſo from the Sence of a future Puniſhment, and the Conſideration of Religion and another World.</p>
            <p>The very <hi>Temper</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> is againſt
<hi>Reſiſting;</hi> it commands Meekneſs and Quietneſs,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93236:9"/>Peaceableneſs and Gentleneſs, the bearing of Injuries patiently from private perſons, much more from our Governours; the bearing the Croſs, and ſuffering all the Evils in the World, rather than doing the leaſt; the <hi>not revenging our ſelves, but rather giving place unto Wrath;</hi> and all thoſe Duties that take off that turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and furious, and unquiet Diſpoſition, from whence the <hi>reſiſting of Governours</hi> proceeds; all thoſe
<hi>Rebellious Luſts,</hi> from whence come Civil Wars and <hi>Fightings</hi> among us: And it is very ſtrange therefore that Religion ſhould ever put men upon that which it ſo expreſly forbids, that men ſhould think it law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to reſiſt their Governours, upon the Account of that which plainly diſallows any ſuch thing. <hi>Popery</hi> is a Religion moſt corrupt and dangerous to the Souls of Men; and therefore to be oppoſed by all lawful ways by every honeſt Man; but to <hi>reſiſt and rebell</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our Governours for the fear of it; nay, for the thing it ſelf, ſhould God in his Judgment bring it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, is what the Goſpel forbids upon pain of Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and what the firſt Chriſtians never did againſt <hi>Paganiſm;</hi> and yet they were as hearty Enemies to that as we can be againſt <hi>Popery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. I might add in the third place, that Reſiſtance is moſt contrary to the
<hi>Conſtitution of our own Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> to the Fundamental Eſtabliſhments of it; the many publick Acts and Declarations that are made concerning it; and the many Oaths by which we are reſtrained againſt it; it would be tedious to name theſe here; and there are few can be iguorant of them, who are themſelves bound to take, and I hope they think themſelves bound alſo to keep them, tho' there have been ſome who have forgot all thoſe, and could as eaſily unlooſe them, as <hi>Sampſon</hi> did his Withs; and then ſet themſelves free from the Precepts &amp; Examples
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93236:10"/>of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and the Primitive Chriſtians, by this
<hi>Colour</hi> and <hi>Pretence,</hi> that the Government under which they lived, was of another Nature than ours is in <hi>England;</hi> and that ſuch is our Conſtitution, as makes all thoſe impertinent, and of very little Regard here: And by the ſame way, might they not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge Wives, and Children, and Servants from thoſe Duties the Goſpel requires of each of them? Becauſe there was great Difference between the State and Condition of thoſe among the
<hi>Jews,</hi> the <hi>Romans,</hi> and the <hi>Grecians</hi> formerly, and <hi>with us now.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I confeſs, had we ſuch a Government as the <hi>Lace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demonians</hi> under their
<hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Ephori,</hi> or as is in ſome other places, where the true
<hi>Sovereignty</hi> is not as it is here in the <hi>Prince,</hi> they might run the Queſtion into this, who were the <hi>Higher Powers,</hi> to whom <hi>Obedience</hi> and
<hi>Non-reſiſtance</hi> did belong, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Scriptures? But no <hi>Engliſh man</hi> can have reaſon to doubt of that here, who knows the <hi>Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of our own Kingdom,</hi> and can no more be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant who has the <hi>Sovereign Power,</hi> than a Servant, who is the Maſter of the Houſe he lives in.</p>
            <p n="4">4. As <hi>Reſiſtance</hi> of our Governours is againſt the Examples, and the Principles of Chriſtianity; and alſo contrary to the Conſtitution of our own Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; ſo 'tis contrary alſo, to <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Equity,</hi> and moſt prejudicial to the
<hi>Good of the World,</hi> and the <hi>Welfare of Mankind:</hi> For what would be the Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of it, but perpetual Tumult and Diſorder, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion and Anarchy. Government was deſigned for the publick Benefit of the World, and next to the Being of a God, and a Providence, 'tis that which preſerves, and is the greateſt Bleſſing to Mankind; which ſecures our Lives from Violence, our Eſtates from Rapine; and is a common Fence, or Hedge, that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93236:10"/>encloſes whatever we enjoy in Safety and Security; and if it were lawful to break this down upon every Pett and Diſtaſte againſt our Governours, we ſhould but lay all open, and in Common again, and become a Prey, and a Spoil to the moſt ſtrong and crafty: If we might reſiſt, and fall to Force and Violence, whenever we liked not what was done by our Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours, then we ſhould be no longer Subjects than we thought fit our ſelves: Their Authority over us ſhould laſt no longer than we our ſelves judged it to ſuit with our Intereſt, or Humor, or Inclination; and then it would be impoſſible to provide either for Peace or Juſtice, or attain any of the Ends for which Government was deſigned and eſtabliſh'd.</p>
            <p>It is poſſible indeed that ſome Inconveniencies may happen ſometimes to Mankind, by their Governours abuſing their Power and Authority, and uſing it to ſerve their own Wills and Pleaſures, rather than pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Good, and the Welfare of thoſe who are under them. This I queſtion not, but may happen, and often has ſo and did ſo, eſpecially under <hi>thoſe Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours,</hi> to whom yet the Scripture commanded <hi>Obedience</hi> and
<hi>Non-reſiſtance;</hi> but there is much leſs Miſchief likely to befall Mankind from thence then there would, if they ſhould be allowed to diſobey and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt as they thought fitting.</hi> It is not poſſible to prevent all manner of Inconveniencies, and ſecure our ſelves againſt all poſſible Evils in this World; but whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver great ones Mankind may lie open to, from the <hi>Princes abuſe of his Power,</hi> to the vioalting of his Subjects Rights and Properties; yet there would be abundantly more and greater, if either upon our Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes or Jealouſies, or the unreaſonable Fears and Pretences of deſigning and unpeaceable Men, it were lawful to <hi>reſiſt,</hi> and make a <hi>forcible Oppoſition</hi> againſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93236:11"/>our Governours. And for this very Reaſon, I que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion not but that God, who deſigns the greateſt good to Mankind that here we are capable of, has thus fix'd and determined it; and if Men would well confider it, they might ſee the Reaſonableneſs and Equity, and even the Neceſſity of its being ſo; but I haſte to the ſecond thing, which is chiefly here meant by <hi>ſtretching out the Hand,</hi> and that is the <hi>murdering and taking away the Life of God's anointed;</hi> and 'tis that for which our Nation does <hi>Penance</hi> this day, and is the greateſt Reproach to our Nation and Religion.</p>
            <p>The horrible Guilt of this I ſhall repreſent in two Particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. From the Conſideration that he was <hi>God's a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed,</hi> which was that which made <hi>David</hi> not dare to do ſo <hi>impious</hi> a thing, <hi>i. e.</hi> one appointed or ordained of God, as all Princes and Governours are: For <hi>there is no Power but of God, the Powers that be, are ordained of God.</hi> Rom. 13.2. that is, that Authority by which <hi>King's Reign,</hi> and <hi>Princes decree Juſtice,</hi> is imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately from God, as the
<hi>Fountain</hi> of all Power and Authority, and the <hi>chief Sovereign</hi> of the World, from whom all others do truly receive theirs. The Word <hi>anointed,</hi> was uſed from the Cuſtom of anointing Princes by God's Command, as a Ceremony of Inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiture and Inauguration of them to their Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but it is given alſo to thoſe to whom God hath given <hi>Sovereign Power and Authority without</hi> that; as <hi>Cyrus</hi> is called the Lord's anointed, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45 1. tho' the way of anointing was not in uſe among the <hi>Perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God, as he was pleaſed to imprint his own <hi>Image</hi> and <hi>Likeneſs</hi> upon Humane Nature, ſo to Princes and Governours he communicates ſome of his own <hi>Power,</hi> and
<hi>Greatneſs,</hi> and <hi>Majeſty;</hi> and they are his imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93236:11"/>
               <hi>Deputies</hi> and <hi>Vicegerents</hi> commiſſionated as it were to govern and rule, and order this Lower World; and therefore are ſtiled <hi>Gods,</hi> and have the Name even of <hi>Elohim,</hi> given them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.6. and then if it be a kind of reſiſting God, and a reſiſting the Ordinance of God to reſiſt them, what is it to
<hi>murder,</hi> and take away the Lives of theſe <hi>Earthly Gods,</hi> thoſe who are anointed and commiſſionated, ordained and appointed by God himſelf? If it be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted
<hi>Treaſon</hi> by Humane Laws, to kill a <hi>Judge</hi> or a <hi>Juſtice</hi> upon the Bench, or an Inferiour Magiſtrate in the perſormance of his Office, becauſe he bears the
<hi>Perſon,</hi> as it were of the King; then is it not <hi>Crimen laeſae Majeſtatis divinae,</hi> a Treaſon againſt God, and of the higheſt Nature, to <hi>deſtroy</hi> and
<hi>murder</hi> one that is God's immediate <hi>Deputy</hi> and <hi>Commiſſioner,</hi> and an Officer appointed to govern ſuch a part of the World under him?</p>
            <p n="2">2. It has all the Guilt in it of the moſt horrid Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; for ſuch is taking away the Life of any Man, without a juſt Power and Authority; and this is committed only to the Governour by God, who is the <hi>Lord of Life and of Death;</hi> and as this is wholly derived from God, and plainly ſhews, that the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate has this his Power wholly from him, and not from the People, becauſe they who have not Power over their own Lives, can never give that to the Prince which they have not themſelves; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this <hi>jus Gradii,</hi> this Power over Mens Lives muſt come <hi>immediately</hi> from God to the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> and ſince God has declared, that <hi>Vengeance is his,</hi> Rom. 12.19. eſpecially that Vengeance which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in all Capital Puniſhments, the <hi>Ruler</hi> muſt be his Miniſter to <hi>execute Vengeance</hi> in this manner, and to this Degree, to all that do ſuch Evil as deſerves it,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93236:12"/>
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4. For he is this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>Revenger,</hi> by an Authority received, immediately from God, and not from Men, who have not ſuch a Power and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over themſelves, and therefore cannot trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it to him; from whence therefore ſhall the <hi>People,</hi> or the whole Community challenge to themſelves this Power over the Life of <hi>their Sovereign,</hi> ſince the Power over their Lives is committed to him only by God? As the pretending this is the uſurping upon the Divine Authority, ſo 'tis the moſt
<hi>horrid</hi> and <hi>vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanous Murder</hi> in the World, not only of a Man, who bears the
<hi>Image of God,</hi> which was <hi>the reaſon</hi> given a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Homicide, Gen.</hi>
9.6. but of a King, who bears the Image of God upon another Account alſo, as he has ſome Rays of the <hi>Divine Majeſty</hi> and <hi>Greatneſs,</hi> and <hi>Authority,</hi> communicated to him above other Men; and it is no way an Abatement, but an Aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the Crime to do this in a pompous way of <hi>ludicrous</hi> and <hi>pretended Juſtice:</hi> For that is as if a Company of <hi>Robbers,</hi> before they took away a Man's Purſe, ſhould bring him to ſome of their Fellows, and they tell him, that property was an Encroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon the natural Right that all Mankind equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly had to the things of the World; and becauſe he had <hi>traiterouſly and feloniouſly</hi> infring'd this, and other Rights and Priviledges that belong'd to them, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they condemn'd him to deliver his Purſe imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately. Juſt ſuch a
<hi>Mock</hi>-thing as this was the <hi>High Court of Juſtice;</hi> and juſt ſo much Power had they to <hi>condemn and murder their anointed Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if all <hi>Murder</hi> be a Sin that cries loud to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for Vengeance, and brings a Guilt, not only up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the particular Shedders; but <hi>defileth a Land,</hi> as God expreſly ſays, <hi>Numb.</hi> 35.33. And even an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93236:12"/>Murder was to be expiated by all that lived within any <hi>City</hi> of ſuch a Diſtance from it, <hi>Deut</hi> 21. Then what Vengeance may we think due, beſides what we have felt already for the <hi>Blood of our Late Martyr'd Sovereign?</hi> And how ſhall this
<hi>City,</hi> that was, I am ſure, at no great <hi>diſtance,</hi> the neareſt I doubt on all accounts, to this <hi>bloody Murder,</hi> be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piated and atoned from it? Let us uſe that Prayer that was appointed in that Caſe, tho' God knows in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely below and unlike ours, with which I ſhall conclude: <hi>Be merciful, O Lord, unto thy People Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, whom thou haſt redeemed,</hi> whom thou haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed at laſt from the Slavery and the Cruelty of thoſe bloody and violent Men, and <hi>lay not innocent Blood unto thy People of Iſraels Charge;</hi> and God grant that this Blood may be forgiven unto this Kingdom; and that for the ſake of that precious Blood of Chriſt, which ſpeaketh better things than the Blood of <hi>Abel,</hi> or the Blood of <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt.</p>
            <closer>Now to God the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, be all Honour and Glory, Praiſe and Thanksgiving, both now, and for evermore.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:93236:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:93236:13"/>
            <head>A SERMON UPON THE THANKSGIVING, For the <hi>Deliverance</hi> of the KING and KINGDOM From the Late Treaſonable <hi>CONSPIRACY.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 SAM. 26.9.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For who can ſtretch forth his Hand againſt the Lord's anointed, and be guiltleſs?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I Begun a Diſcourſe to you on theſe Words the laſt Thirtieth of <hi>January;</hi> the day wherein our Nation ſtands infamous to Poſterity, for the Murder of our Late <hi>Martyred Sovereign:</hi> How many ſuch <hi>black Days</hi> are we to have, to ſtain and diſcredit our
<hi>Engliſh Kalendar?</hi> Will the <hi>Traitors</hi> of our Nation equal the Number of the
<hi>Romiſh Saints?</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:93236:14"/>They will in time, I doubt not, bid fair for it, and very much out do them, had they but every one a day: But it is to be hoped, Poſterity will be ſo kind to us, as to think the <hi>Villany</hi> of the one as incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible as the <hi>Miracles</hi> of the other; and put
<hi>our Plots</hi> in the ſame Rank with <hi>their fabulous Legends;</hi> elſe we had need of another ſort of <hi>Act of Oblivion,</hi> that may make <hi>Time</hi> forget as well as
<hi>Law;</hi> and blot out our Reproach to after Ages. How will it elſe look to thoſe who ſhall have recovered their <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and Loyalty, that their
<hi>Anceſtors,</hi> who were nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wild, nor barbarous, ignorant, nor irreligious, ſhould yet ſtand upon Record for doing ſuch things as the <hi>darkeſt Paganiſm</hi> did never allow, nor the <hi>ſava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt people</hi> ſcarce ever commit?</p>
            <p>One of the beſt Princes that ever ſate, not only upon the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> but upon any Throne, brought as a <hi>Malefactor</hi> before the Bench of his meaneſt Subjects, when every man in the Kingdom can claim his Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of being tryed only by his Peers; condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned there by a
<hi>Mock Scene</hi> of Juſtice, and barbarou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly executed upon a <hi>Scaffold</hi> before his own <hi>Palace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſhould I now tell you of the Excellent Son of that Good Father, murdered by as vile, but a more ſecret way, by a Company of <hi>bloody Villains,</hi> lying in Wait and Ambuſh for him, making His Sacred Body the Mark of their murdering Weapons, and levelling their loaded
<hi>Blunderbuſſes</hi> at their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigns Heart: That <hi>Heart</hi> which had always ſo much Clemency and Tenderneſs for his worſt Enemies; and ſpared even many of their Lives, who are now, without Pity, taking away his: Should I tell you how many gaping Wounds they made in his
<hi>Royal Breaſt;</hi> and how the precious Blood guſh'd from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Artery, and ran down from every open Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:93236:14"/>like common Water ſpilt upon the Ground, till the <hi>anointed of the Lord,</hi> thus uſed by <hi>mercileſs Villains,</hi> lay gaſping and beſmeared in his own, and his Brothers Blood. Lord, how dreadful is it to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe or imagine what they would have committed! And when they had done this, they could ſtop at no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; but go on like thirſty
<hi>Blood-hounds,</hi> to kill and deſtroy, to <hi>maſſacre</hi> thouſands of his faithful Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, to attend their beloved <hi>Prince,</hi> till they had made Rivers of Blood flow in every Street, and fill'd every place with Slaughter and Confuſion: Should I tell you all this, and lay open ſo bloody a Scene before your Eyes, 'twould be but the very Hiſtory of the late intended Tragedy, of that <hi>Helliſh Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> which Heaven, whom we thank this day, and can never ſufficiently thank all our Lives, has deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd us from: When we look back upon it, and view the Danger we have eſcaped, the pleaſing Horrour confounds us, and ſcarce leaves us Sences to be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful as we ought. I ſhall therefore take off your thoughts a little from the thing it ſelf, and put you upon think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what it can ever be, that ſhould engage men in ſuch
<hi>ſtupendous Villanies</hi> as theſe: what helliſh Charms can ever draw men into ſuch
<hi>abominable Deſigns;</hi> and how thoſe, who call themſelves <hi>Men</hi> and
<hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and, what they are more fond of than either, <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants,</hi> ſhould be guilty of what is ſo contrary and reproachful to all thoſe Honourable Names.</p>
            <p>It had been nothing ſo ſtrange, if theſe men had been of a Religion, whoſe very Make is Treaſonable, which has mingled <hi>Treaſon</hi> even with its <hi>Offices of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> and its <hi>Articles of Faith.</hi> Had they been of that Church, which obliges thoſe of its Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to worſhip <hi>Traitors</hi> as <hi>Saints,</hi> and to hold <hi>depoſing of Kings</hi> as a <hi>Catholick Doctrine:</hi> Had they owned
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93236:15"/>thoſe General Councils that have decreed this, and acknowledged that Infallible Head, who could in <hi>Cathedra</hi> commend the Aſſaſſination of a Prince, and compare it to the beſt Actions in Scripture, next our Saviour dying for Mankind: It had not been half ſo much to be wondred at, if they had thus ſuckt <hi>Treaſon</hi> from the Breaſts of their <hi>Roman Mother,</hi> or been nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up in it at a <hi>Popiſh Seminary;</hi> then it would have been but natural to have had the Poyſon broke out ſometime or other into
<hi>Plots,</hi> if the Seaſon had been fair, and outward Circumſtances not driven it in. But to renounce <hi>Popery</hi> with great Zeal, and yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain what is the moſt
<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtian</hi> in it, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to <hi>Proteſtancy;</hi> and yet allow what every
<hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Church</hi> in the World condemns, is to reſolve to be a <hi>Traitor,</hi> and to be of no <hi>Religion</hi> at all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Treaſon</hi> in Papiſts, is like Original Sin to Mankind; they all have it in their Natures, though many of them may deny it, or not know it; and tho' it break not out in all to the ſame outward Extravagancies; but in Proteſtants it is like the <hi>Italian Diſtemper,</hi> it was firſt brought from another Country, and is no way natural to our own, tho' the Infection has been taken by too many, who had an ill Temper pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for it, and others, if they take not Care, are liable to catch it by the Lewdneſs of Ambition, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, or Diſcontent.</p>
            <p>There is no Church in the World that I know of, but the <hi>Romiſh,</hi> which teaches
<hi>Treaſon:</hi> I wiſh I could ſay, there were no Men but they who did ſo; but if there be too many, it cannot however with Juſtice be charg'd upon any <hi>Proteſtant Church,</hi> who all diſown it; any more than <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> or <hi>Polygamy</hi> can be charged to the
<hi>Church of</hi> Rome, becauſe ſome of their Members have defended, and beenguilty of thoſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:93236:15"/>Crimes; but where ever it is in <hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>Presbyter,</hi> in Conclave or Claſſis, in <hi>Jeſuite</hi> or <hi>Fanatick,</hi> 'tis to be abhorred, deteſted, abominated by every good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian; and he that can think upon it without doing ſo, and not let his Heart and his Tongue riſe up againſt it, may in time I doubt, be brought to commit it.</p>
            <p>Stretching out the hand to reſiſt the Prince is moſt plainly unlawful, as I ſhowed you formerly, from the Examples and the Principles of the Chriſtian Religion, from the Conſtitution of our own Government, and from the conſideration of the publick Good and Peace of the World; and that to Murder, or take away his Life, is the moſt horrid guilt that can be; I then un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood that Phraſe of <hi>Stretching out the hand</hi> in both thoſe Senſes, and ſo it takes in both the Parts of this <hi>preſent Conſpiracy;</hi> and indeed though Monſters do not uſe to be alike, yet this does ſo much reſemble that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Treaſon</hi> in its main parts and in its manner of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction, that I could think of nothing fitter to ſhew the
<hi>Villany</hi> of this, and to antidote mens minds againſt the like, for the future, then by reviving the ſame thoughts in your minds, and by proceeding further on the ſame Subject; and eſpecially in that Method which ſhall meet with thoſe Objections which are brought againſt that Duty of <hi>Nonreſiſtance;</hi> thoſe are chiefly ſome <hi>outlying</hi> Caſes as they account them, which come not into this general Duty, but are Exemptions from it; and theſe are they by which Men are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally drawn into <hi>Treaſon,</hi> which is a Sin too ugly in its looks to tempt Men, if it wore not a Vizard. 'Tis theſe Caſes which by a <hi>Rebellious Witchcraft,</hi> are caſt like Miſts before Mens eyes, and ſo they are jugled and ſeduced into the ſaddeſt <hi>Treaſons</hi> and <hi>Conſpiracies;</hi> though a great many of them are like the Propoſals of <hi>Mathematicians,</hi> to move the Earth if you grant them
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:93236:16"/>ſuch and ſuch <hi>Poſtulala,</hi> and allow things to be ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered as they would ſuppoſe, which can never be really done, and the Earth is in no danger to be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for all their Demonſtrations; yet theſe Men do really move the Kingdom, and turn it out of its place by fancied and Romantick Caſes, which it is impoſſible perhaps, ſhould ever come into practice. But I intend to conſider ſuch Caſes as are thought more probable and plauſible, and which are the common <hi>Stumbling-blocks</hi> that lie in the way of this Duty, and cauſe a great many, as they did our <hi>preſent Conſpirators,</hi> to fall into that <hi>Treaſonable Gulph,</hi> which wholly ſwallows them up, if they come too near the brink of it.</p>
            <p>They are theſe four.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Caſe of Religion, The Caſe of Legal Rights, The Caſe of Natural Defence, and the otherwiſe Remedileſs Caſe of Mankind, by the Encroachment of</hi> Princes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The Caſe of Religion, which is the greateſt and moſt important Concern to Mankind, wherein their Souls and their Eternal Fortunes lie all at ſtake; and both they and their Poſterity may looſe what is more valuable then their Lives or Eſtates, if they ſtand not up ſometimes and fight for their God and their Altars, which were Conſiderations that always inſpired Men with the greateſt Courage and Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If a Prince ſhall ſet up a falſe and Idolatrous Religion, and attempt to deſtroy the true Worſhip of God, here they think, both a Zeal for him and Religion, and a Care of their own and their Poſterities Salvation, calls loudly upon them to reſiſt him to the utmoſt, and with the noble</hi> Macca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bees, <hi>to ſhed the laſt drop of their Blood for their Religion and their Temple. If the</hi> Proteſtant Religion <hi>be like to be overthrown and</hi> Popery <hi>to be brought in, this is ſuch an allarum to thoſe who love the one and hate the other, as will
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:93236:16"/>not fail to bring in vaſt numbers forcibly to</hi> Reſiſt <hi>that Prince who ſhall ever attempt it; and think it their duty ſo to do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I ſhall give this general Anſwer.</p>
            <p>That we may ſhow our Zeal and our Love to our Religion, a better way then by thus
<hi>Reſiſting</hi> and Fighting for it, for that is to do what our Religion expreſly forbids, which can no way conſiſt with that love we ſhould have for it; They who are ſuch Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants for their Religion, as immediately to draw and fight for it, do commonly abuſe and proſtitute it to ſome ill and Carnal ends, and are ſeldom ſuch chaſte, and conſtant, and pure Lovers of it, as they pretend. Our Saviour and his Apoſtles had without doubt as much love for Chriſtianity, and were as zealous to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve and maintain it as we can be, but yet never thought fit to ſhow it this way, by <hi>Reſiſting</hi> the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority that then was, though it did all it could to deſtroy it.</p>
            <p>There is another, and a much better way to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate the higheſt Affection for our Religion, and that is by ſuffering for it, and enduring all manner of Evils rather then forſaking it; and this is a like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier Method to preſerve and propagate it, and to tranſmit it down to Poſterity both with ſafety and credit; By this very way Chriſtianity has come down to us, in a Channel of blood indeed, but that drawn from its own Friends and Profeſſors who laid down their Lives for it, but not the leaſt drop from its Enemies.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Maccabees</hi> were zealous indeed for their Law, and fought for it, but not againſt their own <hi>Lawful Prince,</hi> but an Enemy that invaded them, for ſuch was
<hi>Antiochus,</hi> who uſed all manner of provoking
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:93236:17"/>Impiety and barbarous Cruelty againſt the <hi>Jews</hi> who were not his rightful Subjects, and might therefore reſcue themſelves from his Oppreſſion and unjuſt Uſurpation.</p>
            <p>At other times when any of the <hi>Jewiſh Kings</hi> ſet up Idolatry, and Worſhipt
<hi>Baal</hi> or other Falſe Gods, none of the <hi>Prophets</hi> who were the mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt zealous Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of their <hi>Law,</hi> and rebuked the <hi>Princes</hi> for thoſe Faults to their very Faces, did yet ever call upon the
<hi>Elders,</hi> or encourage the People to <hi>Reſiſt</hi> them, or to fight for their Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Popery</hi> is an abominable and <hi>Idolatrous Religion,</hi> the moſt corrupt of any Sect or Party that calls it ſelf Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and the moſt dangerous to the Souls of Men, but
'tis a better way to keep it out with our <hi>Hands bound to the Stake,</hi> then <hi>ſtretcht out againſt our Lawful Sovereign;</hi> and we ſhall ſhow our love to <hi>Proteſtancy</hi> much better, by dying for it our ſelves, if need be, then by killing others. One Life of our own Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to it, is a Nobler Offering, and more acceptable to God and our Saviour, than a thouſand Victims at the expence of other Mens Lives.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>If Men may not Reſiſt purely for Religion and to defend that, yet when they have</hi> Law <hi>on their ſides, either for their Religion or any thing elſe, and their Princes who are bound to</hi> keep the Law, <hi>will yet act againſt it, and deſpoil them of their Civil Rights and Priviledges, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade their Properties and deſtroy their Religion contrary to Law, and to the ſetled Conſtitutions of the Kingdom; then ſurely they may forcibly deſend their Laws, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently their Religion, or any thing that is thus twiſted and complicated with their Laws which it is not in the Princes power to alter or unlooſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I ſhall return a Treble Anſwer.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:93236:17"/>
            <p n="1">1. If the Law had made a Proviſion and expreſly allow'd Reſiſtance, when any ſuch Caſes ſhould hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, however fooliſh a Conſtitution that had been, yet the Caſe had been much ſtronger, and the nullity of the allowance not ſo eaſie to be made out, as in the <hi>German</hi> Empire there is ſuch a Proviſion made, that if the Emperour invade the
<hi>Eſtabliſht Rights</hi> of the <hi>Princes,</hi> who though they are Sovereigns in their own Territories, yet are ſworn Subjects to him, they may take Arms, and ſuch a Capitulation there was formerly between the <hi>King of Spain</hi> and the <hi>Low Countries;</hi> but in our Kingdom there is plainly no ſuch thing, and care has been taken that none ſhould ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that there was any ſuch kind of <hi>tacit</hi> or <hi>implicit</hi> condition, the Law making an expreſs
<hi>Declaration</hi> to the contrary, to wit, <hi>That it is unlawful to reſiſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any account whatſoever,</hi> which puts the thing out of all manner of diſpute, that we cannot
<hi>by Law</hi> reſiſt though it be to defend what we have by Law, for that would be to act againſt one expreſs Law, whilſt we were defending another.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As long as the <hi>Power of the Sword</hi> is wholly in the <hi>King</hi> by the Law of God and of Man, who ſhall ever uſe or draw it without an authority derived from him? From whence elſe ſhall any Man have a <hi>Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> to <hi>raiſe Companies,</hi> to array an Army, to be a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander or a General over them, and to uſe that force which is often neceſſary for the execution of Juſtice, and giving force to Laws? for without that they are often but dead Letters, and therefore no Man can be the <hi>Guardian of the Laws,</hi> who is not the <hi>Keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Sword,</hi> which is committed to the <hi>Prince</hi> alone.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:93236:18"/>
            <p n="3">3. If a Prince will injure his Subjects, and invade their Rights, nay, and their Lives
<hi>againſt Law;</hi> when they have tried all other means, they muſt as Chriſt did patiently ſubmit to an <hi>unjuſt Sentence,</hi> rather then reſiſt; and, as the firſt Chriſtians did, who often com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd that they were puniſht <hi>adverſus formam, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſus naturam judicandi, contra ipſus quoque leges,</hi> Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tull. Apologet. <hi>c.</hi> 2. and that their Perſecutors would not let them have the ſame benefit of the <hi>Roman</hi> Laws with others,
<hi>aliter in nos quàm in caeteros nocentes diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitis,</hi> ibid. and yet the great numbers he there tells them they had, did not put them upon <hi>Reſiſting;</hi> and as St.
<hi>Paul</hi> did, who though inconſiderately, and in Paſſion, he call'd the High-Prieſt a Whited-wall, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>when he ſat to Judge him after the Law, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him to be ſmitten contrary to the Law,</hi> Acts 23.3. yet he preſently acknowledged his fault, and own'd, that he ſhould not have ſo much as <hi>ſpoke evil</hi> of a Ruler, though he puniſht him <hi>illegally</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Law, and therefore much leſs have
<hi>Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted</hi> him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>But though the Law of the Land forbids Reſiſtance, yet the</hi> Law of Nature,
<hi>which no other Law can ſuperſede, will allow it for our own neceſſary defence and</hi> Self-Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation; <hi>that is ſuch a natural Right as can never be taken from us, and no Man can ever be ſuppoſed to part withal. By this we may take away anothers Life in our own defence, and yet fall under no Law of God or Man for it, and by this a Prince may be reſiſted as well as a Robber, if he will take away my Goods or my Life as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly as he.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I ſhall Anſwer Three things.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:93236:18"/>
            <p n="1">1. The Law of Nature can at moſt, be ſaid only to <hi>permit</hi> this, not to
<hi>enjoyn</hi> it; if there were a <hi>Right</hi> of Nature that <hi>allow'd</hi> this, yet there cannot be a <hi>Law</hi> that <hi>commanded</hi> it, and <hi>obliged</hi> us to it, but a Man might ſtill part with his Natural Right without any fault, and it would be an <hi>Heroick</hi> inſtance of Vertue to do ſo, rather to give our own Life, or part with any Private Intereſt of our own, then take away the Life of another Man, and this to be ſure, is much the ſafer ſide, which is out of all danger and undoubtedly lawful, when there are great Reaſons to fear that Reſiſting even in that Caſe may prove Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Poſitive Conſtitutions</hi> may limit and reſtrain Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Right in this or any other Caſe, or elſe all Pacts and Covenants are in vain; nay, and all Civil Laws whatſoever, becauſe they do all of them, reſtrain Men from that which before they had a Natural Right to; and if we cannot by any means be abridged of that, then there is an end not only of all Government, but of all Property too, and Mankind may return into a <hi>Wild State of Nature,</hi> when ever they pleaſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Though the Law of Nature allows us to reſiſt private Violence in our own defence, yet it does not to reſiſt the Publick Magiſtrate, for that would be deſtructive of publick good and injurious to the Peace and Welfare of Mankind, which the other is not; and though I may fairly ſtand upon my defence when there is only a competition between my own and anothers private good, yet I muſt not do it when the Competition is between the publick good, and my own private; whoever conſiders himſelf as a Member of the vaſt Body of Mankind, or of a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Kingdom, muſt think it as unreaſonable and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd to prefer his own private good to the publick, as
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:93236:19"/>to believe a <hi>ſingle part</hi> to be as great as the <hi>whole;</hi> This is the Prime and Fundamental Law of Nature, to promote as far as we are able, the publick good, and endeavour to increaſe, not ſo much our own private ſhare, as the common and publick ſtock of Happineſs which belongs to the whole Company and Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, in which our own is likewiſe included; and never to think that our own private and particular intereſt is to be put in the Ballance with that, and there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more ſtrong againſt Reſiſtance which would not fail to bring in the greateſt publick Miſchief to avoid a leſs and more private one, then this very Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, which is the true meaſure, however large, of Moral good and evil, and the very Foundation of all the Laws of Nature.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>If neither upon the account of Religion, nor Laws, nor yet Self defence, it be lawful to reſiſt the Prince, then Mankind is left in a Remedileſs Caſe and Condition, and muſt lie open to the continual Encroachments and Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of their Governours, and notwithſtanding all Laws for their ſecurity, yet if they muſt not ſtand up to defend, and if need be to fight for thoſe Laws, they are in the ſame condition as if they had none, for the Prince may break thoſe Spiders Webs when he pleaſes, and only uſe them as a Snare to catch others in; he may enſlave and murder us when he pleaſes, if he may not be Reſiſted when he thinks fit to do ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I Anſwer.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We muſt never expect to find out a Remedy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all poſſible Inconveniencies in this World, in this low and imperfect State we ſhall always be ſubject to ſome publick as well as private Evils, the <hi>body poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick</hi> will never be free from all manner of Infirmities
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:93236:19"/>and Diſeaſes any more then the body <hi>Natural,</hi> ſuch a
<hi>Temperamentum ad pondus</hi> can never be expected in ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as ſhall keep them from all illneſs at preſent, or corruption at the laſt.</p>
            <p>There can no more be a perfect Government, ſuch as we would fain imagine to our ſelves, then there can be a perfect Circle or ſtreight line ſuch as <hi>Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticians</hi> ſuppoſe;
<hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Mankind</hi> will not be brought to that exactneſs, but that ſome unevenneſs and irregularity will belong to both, and if we ſhould go about to pare all thoſe off, the incapacity of the Subject would not admit it, and we ſhould probably by our trying make them much worſe then they were before, an endeavour to patch up and amend the neceſſary Imperfections that attend this our preſent State, has made them commonly much greater and wider, as <hi>Paracelſus</hi> kill'd himſelf in his Youth by endeavouring to make himſelf Immortal.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Papiſts,</hi> to prevent all poſſibility of Errour in Divine things, which God has not, and I'm ſure, Man cannot make ſuch a Proviſion againſt as they would have, have brought in an Infallible Teacher into the Church, as a neceſſary and plauſible Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to keep out all Hereſie and Errour that elſe we might be ſubject to fall into; and ſee the good of this notable device of theirs, it has brought more Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors and more dangerous and incurable ones into Chriſtianity, then it would ever have had with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it.</p>
            <p>The Projectors of the late times would have the Prince accountable to the People to prevent the ill uſe of his Power and Authority, but never was more Miſchief done then by that Traiterous Device, and the People could never have been in a worſe caſe under the moſt grievous Tyranny, then under
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:93236:20"/>ſuch Anarchy and Confuſion; They who ſhould take account of the Prince, like the Ephori or the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunes, who ſhould take account of them? and who again of them? we muſt run into an infinite Circle, or we muſt ſtop ſomewhere, and where ever we do we ſhall be juſt in the ſame caſe.</p>
            <p>There muſt be unaccountable Sovereignty ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, whatever <hi>Politick Abſurdities</hi> we may think follow from it, as there muſt be an indiviſible part of matter at the laſt, whatever Difficulties Philoſophy may charge it with.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A Legal Conſtitution, eſpecially ſo good an one as our own, is a great ſecurity to us: This makes a Kingdom like a curious and well-made Machine fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly framed and joined together in its ſeveral parts, the <hi>Prince</hi> is the greater Wheel, and the firſt Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Motion in it, and the <hi>Law</hi> is like a Pendulum that <hi>evens and regulates</hi> that Motion, and though not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that he ſhould happen to be irregular, yet he would hardly be able to ſpoil the whole Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaniſm, and make all the under <hi>wheels</hi> and other parts move contrary to their true make and ſhape, which the Law has given them; the ſubordinate Officers are not bound to act illegally, and would not eaſily be brought to it againſt their Oaths and their Intereſts, when they know they may be puniſht here, and ſhall be damned for it hereafter; and whilſt the Hands and the Legs are to execute the Commands of the Head, though they muſt not riſe up againſt that, yet that cannot when it pleaſes put them into an unnatural motion and diſtortion.</p>
            <p>But though the Machine might be diſordered a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle by ſome great ſhake and concuſſion, yet while it is ſo ſtrong, and ſo well made, it would come right again in a little time, and fall into its true make and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:93236:20"/>proper Motion. <hi>Res nolunt diù malè adminiſtrari,</hi> Things would not ſtand long bent by an illegal force, but would by degrees unlooſen themſelves by a kind of natural Elaſticity which the Law gives them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. God's Providence and Government of the World is the beſt ſecurity in this and all other Evils we are ſubject to; <hi>If Parents will grieve their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and be bitter againſt them,</hi> if Princes will injure their Subjects and Tyrannize over them, if a more powerful Prince will like a greater <hi>Pyrat</hi> Rob and Spoil his Neighbours, and make a Prey of them, 'tis God alone they muſt appeal to, and expect to be righted at his Tribunal.</p>
            <p>Princes are God's immediate Officers and Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, and he will take particular inſpection over them, that they abuſe not his People committed to their Charge, to him alone they are accountable, and therefore he who has exempted them from the Cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance of others, will take the Matter into his own hands, and not ſuffer their faults to go unpuniſht; <hi>But who art thou,</hi> O Subject, <hi>who Judgeth thy</hi> Prince? <hi>To his own Maſter he ſtandeth or falleth.</hi> To him they have given a Pledge by their Oaths, and if they break thoſe, <hi>Satis eſt quod Deum expectent ultorem,</hi> It is ſufficient that <hi>he to whom Vengeance belongeth,</hi> is the <hi>Avenger of all ſuch,</hi> and this he is in ſo terrible a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that nothing has felt his Anger more dreadfully then a Tyrant's Conſcience, no body has had more Horrours and Fears, more Stroaks of a Divine Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſis upon him then he that has uſed his Power to cruel and unjuſt Deſigns; the meaneſt of his Vaſſals has not felt ſo much Torment and ſo many Racks from him, as he has done from his own Mind, nor has any half ſo much reaſon to fear his Power as he
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:93236:21"/>has to be afraid of Gods; that great Patron of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and Great Governour of the World, who ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the raging of the Sea and the Madneſs of the People, will ſet bounds alſo to the Power and Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of Princes, and ſo far as is neceſſary for the good of the World, and for his Wiſe Deſigns, <hi>ſo far they ſhall go and no farther,</hi> but like Earthquakes and Tempeſts, and Inundations, we have no ſecurity againſt them, but from the Providence of God.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the chief <hi>Caſes</hi> and <hi>Objections</hi> againſt the Duty of
<hi>Non-Reſiſtance</hi> or not <hi>Stretching out the hand againſt the Lord's Anointed;</hi> and by theſe however Magical Deluſions the Evil Spirit of Rebellion has been conjured up, and ſtill haunteth this Nation, and fills it with Plots and Treaſon, with Noiſe and Miſchief and Diſturbance; and I know no ſuch way to lay it from ever riſing again, as a full and clear Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to thoſe fore-mentioned Caſes which I have endeavoured to give.</p>
            <p>As to the other way of <hi>Stretching out the Hand</hi> to take away the Life of the <hi>Lord's Anointed,</hi> that is ſo Horrid and Villanous, that one would think it ſhould have none to defend it, though it have had ſome to commit it, but there is no cauſe of intereſt ſo bad but it has had its Advocate, and when ever there has been a <hi>Clement</hi> or a
<hi>Ravilliac,</hi> there has been a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor to incourage if not a Pope and an Infallible Orator to commend him; the Opinions of the Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its are well known to be poſitive in the caſe, and others have faſhion'd their Weapons at the Forge of thoſe <hi>Philiſtines</hi> which are to take away the Lives of Princes, and though they are not come to Conſecrate Daggers for the purpoſe, and that becauſe, they are againſt the <hi>Ceremony</hi> rather then the
<hi>Villany,</hi> yet Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtols
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:93236:21"/>and Blunderbuſſes are thought to be Bleſſed In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments for doing the great Work; though they expect not to be Sainted for it and adored in Heaven, yet they expect what they will hardly allow the Saints themſelves, to have their Images erected upon Earth, and Statues ſet up to their honour, and to the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of ſuch Noble Atchievements. Like
<hi>Heroſtratus</hi> they deſign to make their Names Famous by doing ſome extraordinary Villany, and by daring to be wicked beyond the reſt of Mankind, The committing ſuch a Wickedneſs as others are aſtoniſht to think of, is to be an Hero in Villany, and they want nothing to out do what has been ever done, or ever thought of, but with the old Gyants to pluck God out of his Throne, and <hi>ſo to put down all Rule, and all Authority and Power, both in Heaven and Earth.</hi> I cannot think that Men can ſeriouſly argue themſelves into ſuch Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanies as theſe, but it muſt be the very ſame thing that makes the Devil a Rebel to God, which makes theſe Men Regicides, and Traytours to their Sovereign; a Proud, an Envious, a Diſcontented, and Diabolical Spirit that infinite Power cannot awe, nor infinite Goodneſs oblige; but the Devil and a <hi>Scotch Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticler</hi> are ſuch Sophiſters as can ſet off the moſt Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid Villany, and repreſent this <hi>as an Heroick Bravery, and a ſort of Gallantry that the</hi> Grecians <hi>and the</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans <hi>thought fit to be rewarded with Crowns, and Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, and publick Inſigns of Honour; the killing of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants was thought, a Vertue like that of</hi> Hercules, <hi>who deſtroy'd abundance of thoſe Monſters,</hi> &amp; nihil uſitatius quam eorum interfectores in Caelo collocari: <hi>ſays</hi> Tully ad Attic. <hi>l.</hi> 14.
<hi>Ep.</hi> 16. Harmodius <hi>and</hi> Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giton <hi>and others were commended to the Skyes for theſe very Performances; and not only the</hi> Greeks <hi>and the</hi> Romans <hi>did thus commend and honour them, but even
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:93236:22"/>in Scripture,</hi> Jael, <hi>and</hi> Judith, <hi>and</hi> Ehud, Barack,
<hi>and</hi> Deborah, <hi>and thoſe</hi> Jewiſh <hi>Deliverers of their Country ſtand all upon the Records of Fame and the Divine Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation for Murdering Kings and Tyrants that were the Enemies of God and his peculiar People, and when the Cauſe of God and His People, the Cauſe of Religion and Conſcience is the great thing that is to be carried on, who that has a Zeal for thoſe, would not do any thing that is neceſſary for ſo glorious an end?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lucifer</hi> himſelf could hardly have inſtilled worſe Principles into the Angels when he perſuaded them to turn Devils and to forſake their firſt Station: I ſhall give a particular Anſwer to the three Parts that it conſiſts of.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As to the <hi>Grecians</hi> and the <hi>Romans,</hi> when they affixt ſuch worthy Names and Honours to the killers of Tyrants, they did not mean by Tyrants their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Princes but
<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers,</hi> that by force and violence aſſumed an unjuſt Power to themſelves, contrary to the <hi>regular form of Government</hi> that was eſtabliſhed among them, ſuch as had no juſt <hi>Title</hi> to rule by the Laws of their Country, but invaded the Rights of their proper Governours, and <hi>over-turned</hi> the whole Frame of the Common-wealth, and againſt ſuch as theſe they were <hi>empowered</hi> by the eſtabliſht Laws of their
<hi>Country,</hi> by the <hi>Lex Solonis</hi> among the <hi>Greeks,</hi> and the <hi>Lex Valeria</hi> among the <hi>Romans;</hi> and if any were guilty of doing this to their lawful Governours, it muſt be reckoned as part of that <hi>Ferity</hi> and <hi>bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Ignorance</hi> which was in thoſe Nations before Chriſtianity taught them better, when to <hi>kill them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi> was accounted as <hi>Heroic</hi> a Vertue as to <hi>Murder a Tyrant;</hi> but the Sobereſt amongſt them taught otherwiſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:93236:22"/>ſays <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in his <hi>Politicks,</hi> the very Doctrine of
<hi>Non-Reſiſtance,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſays <hi>Plutarch, Agis &amp; Cleom.</hi> The very words almoſt of <hi>David,</hi> It is not lawful to ſtretch forth the hand againſt a Prince, and we have Examples even amongſt both the <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Romans</hi> of the ſame Puniſhment againſt thoſe who were concerned in the Murder of their Princes, that
<hi>David</hi> inflicted upon the <hi>Amalekite</hi> for the Death of <hi>Saul</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi>
1.16. <hi>Alexander</hi> put him to Death who kill'd <hi>Darius</hi> that was his Sovereign, though he had been a great while <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Enemy, and ſo did <hi>Domitian, Nero</hi>'s Freeman, who was but acceſſory to his Maſters Murdering of himſelf.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As to the comparing this Villany with the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Jael,</hi> and
<hi>Judith,</hi> and <hi>Ehud,</hi> and others who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed thoſe their Enemies with whom they were in a <hi>State of War,</hi> or had particular <hi>Commiſſions</hi> from God to
<hi>authorize</hi> them in the doing ſuch <hi>extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary</hi> Atchievements, they might as well, and with as good reaſon argue, that becauſe <hi>David</hi> kill'd <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liah</hi> and deſtroy'd the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> that therefore he might have taken away the Life of
<hi>Saul;</hi> nay, that he might have made no more to kill him then <hi>the Lyon</hi> and the
<hi>Bear,</hi> for God's Anointed are account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by theſe Men, but as a ſort of <hi>Wolves</hi> and <hi>Tygers,</hi> and <hi>Beaſts of prey,</hi> that ought to be deſtroyed; and they may as well make uſe of the Example of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> to Sacrifice and Murder their Children when they pleaſe; as of <hi>Jehu</hi> and others in Scripture, to deſtroy the Houſe and Family of their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:93236:23"/>
            <p n="3">3. As to the laſt thing, that they may do anything for the carrying on a good Cauſe and Deſign, as they will be ſure to call what they are promoting, that if it be the <hi>Work of the Lord,</hi> and the maintaining the true Religion, and the <hi>Proteſtant intereſt,</hi> the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out <hi>Popery</hi> and deſtroying <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> or any ſuch good end they are to accompliſh, they may then do any thing that is neceſſary to this, and not ſtick at any means that come in their way, be they never ſo bad, becauſe a good end and intention will not fail to <hi>hallow</hi> and Sanctifie the whole action, or at leaſt to <hi>expiate</hi> and at one for all the guilt that is in it; This I believe is a Principle that draws in a great many into the moſt villanous and unwarrantable Deſigns, into Treaſons and Murders, and the greateſt Villanies when they think them neceſſary to go through with that great and good
<hi>Cauſe</hi> they have undertaken; and this is an excellent <hi>principle,</hi> like an Elixir that turns the worſt Matter into Gold, to <hi>tranſmute</hi> Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Murder into the pureſt Vertues; and by a certain ſleight of Intention and Spiritual Legerdemain to put the worſt actions in the place of the beſt, and <hi>Hocus Pocus</hi> Vice into Vertue, when ever one pleaſes; Nay, 'tis to deſtroy the very <hi>nature</hi> of good and evil, and to make nothing ſo in its ſelf, but as our own Intentions put a <hi>ſtamp</hi> upon it; if we can but
<hi>graft</hi> a good intention upon never ſo bad an action, this ſhall change the very
<hi>kind,</hi> and make all it bears fair and lovely; one <hi>drop</hi> of this good intention ſhall take away all the venom out of the moſt poyſonous wickedneſs, turn bitter into ſweet, evil into good; it will make good and evil that are naturally and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutably
<hi>fixt,</hi> melt and ſoften in our hands, ſo that we may form and faſhion them as we pleaſe, and makes them meerly <hi>relative</hi> and dependent upon our
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:93236:23"/>Thoughts and Deſigns, which is to deſtroy all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. If a Man do but winck and aim well, tho he Murder his Sovereign, nay, if it were his Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, he ſhould be juſtified by this Principle, and the <hi>Jews</hi> who kill'd Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and
<hi>thought they did God good Service thereby,</hi> as many of them probably did, may plead it in their own full defence. I cannot imagine how any one can have a good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, who ventures upon ſuch plain and notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Villanies, but if theſe be guilded over with ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſuch fair Pretences, and are thought neceſſary for never ſo glorious a deſign, yet
<hi>Reſiſting</hi> and <hi>Murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> the Lord's Anointed are ſo manifeſtly ſinful and unlawful, that <hi>none can do ſuch evil that good may come, but their Damnation muſt be juſt</hi> both with God and Man. But ſad is it when Men ſhall form ſuch Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to themſelves as ſhall lead them into ſuch Helliſh Villanies, when they ſhall think theſe abominable Practiſes not only lawful but neceſſary to <hi>God's Glory,</hi> as if he could not bring about his own ends without their Wickedneſs, but the Devil muſt be called in to aſſiſt God, and to carry on the Cauſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            <p>God preſerve Chriſtianity from that Reproach and Blaſphemy which theſe Wicked Men have brought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it.</p>
            <p>God preſerve the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> from that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage is hereby given our Enemies to deſtroy it.</p>
            <p>He who ordereth all things unto his own Glory, be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to bring good out of this Evil, and make it a means to unite us all unto his Church, and make us Loyal and Faithful unto his Anointed.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:93236:24"/> And for ever bleſſed and praiſed be the Providence of that God who hath brought to light the hidden things of Darkneſs, and has not given us over as a prey to Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thirſty Men, who lay in wait to deſtroy us.</p>
            <p>And thou, O King of Heaven and Earth, who haſt graciouſly delivered thine Anointed from the hands of wicked Men ſtretcht out againſt him, and haſt miraculouſly preſerv'd him from the Plots and Conſpiracies of all his Enemies, keep him always, we beſeech thee, under the ſhadow of thy wings, preſerve him as the Apple of thine Eye, and guard thou his Throne with Legions of Angels, that the Sons of Violence may never approach to hurt him; the Lord preſerve him and keep him alive, that he may be bleſſed upon Earth, and deliver thou not him unto the Will of his Enemies. <hi>Pſal. 41.2.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
